In this module, we are going to focus on Model Context Protocol.
MCP is a communication layer designed to provide Cloud with context and tools
without requiring you, the developer, to write a bunch of tedious code.
When you first get started with MCP, you will see diagrams that look like this
very often. It shows two major elements of MCP, namely the client and the server.
The server often contains a number of internal components,
named tools, resources, and prompts. There's a lot of terminology here,
so to help you understand all of this, we're going to imagine that we are building a small app
and see how MCP fits into it. Our sample app is going to be another
chat interface. It's going to allow a user to chat with Cloud about their GitHub data.
So if a user asks a question like, what open pull request do I have across all my different
repositories, the expectation is that Cloud is probably going to make use of a tool
to reach out to GitHub, access the user's account, and see what open pull requests they have,
maybe open repositories or whatever else. The point here is that we would implement this
probably by using a set of tools. Now one thing I want to mention
really quickly is that GitHub has a tremendous amount of functionality.
There are repositories, pull requests, issues, projects, and tons of other things.
So to have a complete GitHub chatbot, we would really have to author a tremendous number of
tools. If we wanted to build that sample app, we would be on the hook for authoring all these
schemas and all these functions. And this is all code that you and I as developers would have to
write, test, and maintain. That's a lot of effort, a lot of burden being placed on us.
This challenge of making developers maintain a big set of integrations is one of the primary
difficulties that model context aims to solve. MCP shifts the burden of defining and running tools
from your server to something else called an MCP server. So no longer would you and I have to
author this tool right here. Instead, it would be authored and executed somewhere else inside
of this MCP server. These MCP servers can really be thought of as like an interface to some outside
service. So I might have a GitHub MCP server that provides access to data and functionality provided
by specifically GitHub. We're essentially wrapping up a ton of functionality around GitHub and
placing it into this MCP server in the form of a set of tools. So at this point, we have a very
basic understanding of what a MCP server is. It gives us access to a set of tools that exposes
functionality related to some outside service. And the benefit here is that you and I do not
have to author all these different tool schemas and functions and so on. Now that we have this
basic understanding, I want to address some very common questions that a lot of people have when
they first learn about MCP servers. So three common questions that seem to always come up.
The first common question is who authors these MCP servers? And the answer is anyone. Anyone can
make an MCP server implementation. But very often, you will find that service providers make their own
official implementation. So for example, AWS might decide to release their own official
MCP server implementation. And inside of it, it might have a wide variety of different tools
available for you to use. The second common question is how is using a MCP server different
than just calling a services API directly? Well, as we just saw, if we wanted to call a API directly,
such as GitHub, then we would have to author this tool ourselves. And now we can call GitHub directly.
So what did we gain here? Well, all that really changed was we are now having to author the schema
ourselves and the function implementation ourselves. So simply by adding in the MCP server,
we are saving ourselves a little bit of time. The final common question is more of a common
criticism that you're going to see people have around MCP. And this criticism is most often
coming from people who don't quite understand what MCP is all about. So very often, you will
see people saying MCP and tool use are the same thing. Well, as I have just laid out to you,
MCP servers and tool use, they are complementary. They are different things, but they are
complementary. The idea behind MCP is that you do not have to author the tool function and the tool
schema. That is something that's done for you by someone else and is being wrapped up inside of
this MCP server. So at some level, yeah, they're kind of similar because we are talking about tool
use in both cases. But MCP servers are really talking about who is doing the actual work.
So if you ever see this criticism, again,
it's usually because people don't quite understand what MCP is all about.